בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ט, mem-tet, 49. We
pick up at the bottom of מ"ח עמוד ב'. mem-chet amud bet.
Also want to wish everybody a good ערב ערב ל"ג בעומר. erev
erev Lag Ba'Omer. People should be aware according to the רמ"א, Rama,
you're allowed to get a haircut
today, לכבוד שבת, l'kavod Shabbos, just mentioning that, if it's relevant. Okay,
anyway, picking up at the bottom of מ"ח עמוד ב', mem-chet amud
bet, we are now discussing the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
and the רבנן. Rabbanan. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishnah
says if you have a courtyard, three courtyards, and A and B
make an עירוב eiruv and B and C make an עירוב, eiruv,
then you can A and B can carry in their space and
B and C can carry in their space and move around objects
from one of the courtyards to the other.
And the rabbis disagree, and the גמרא Gemara on עמוד א' amud
aleph said that the reason the rabbis disagreed was a concern that
if we let A carry into space B, then he would come
to carry into space C and that way it was different than
the case of three people where there was not a concern of
all of the moving around and confusion. So that was what the
גמרא Gemara first said. Then
the גמרא Gemara wanted to understand
or wanted to explain that why there'd be a reason to disagree.
So we'll pick up again from the bottom of מ"ח עמוד ב'
mem-chet amud bet of
why the חכמים chachamim disagree and this might be different than the
reason of גזירה gezeirah that the גמרא Gemara had initially said. So
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, four lines
from the bottom, זו דברי רבי שמעון. Zu divrei Rabbi Shimon. This
is the position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval
chachamim omrim, that the חכמים chachamim say, רשות אחת משמשת לשתי רשויות
ולא שתי רשויות משמשת לרשות אחת. reshut achat m'shameshet l'shtei reshuyot v'lo
shtei reshuyot m'shameshet l'reshut achat. Well, that's self-explanatory, which is why you
have that huge תוספות Tosfot there. So what רש"י Rashi says that
means is, and I explained this yesterday, I think I'd erased,
and I see that somebody wrote with non-dry erase ink.
Okay, anyway, the way I explained it according to רש"י Rashi was,
if you have you have your A, B, C, right, and they've
made these two types of things. Okay, so the reason to say
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon might not agree about all of that is
the way רש"י Rashi explains it is, A can move into B,
C can move into B, but B can't go to A and
can't go to C because that's pulling it in opposite directions and
B therefore has a contradictory identity. I tried to sort of symbolize
it like this, that if you have B is the main רשות,
reshut, if you're focusing on B, if B tries to move into
A and tries to move into C, it's sort of, that's a
idea of, that's what doesn't work, that's שתי רשויות, shtei reshuyot, A
and C cannot serve B, because B is being pulled both ways.
But you can have this, you know, because
רשות אחת, reshut achat, B can serve both A and C because
there's no contradiction from A's perspective to have an A-B and from
C's perspective to have a C-B. But from B's perspective for B
to carry into A, that would not be good. That's the way
רש"י Rashi explains it as that is a very different reason than
the גמרא Gemara said yesterday, which is the reason of גזירה gezeirah
that said that A can't carry into... that the reason the rabbis
didn't like it is once you allow carrying, it's going to lead
to from A going into C. This is a more principled objection
of conceptually B being pulled in both ways. I should mention however
that תוספות Tosfot disagrees with this read and תוספות Tosfot makes it
consistent with the גמרא's Gemara idea that the reason the חכמים chachamim
disagree is they're afraid it'll lead to a problem, a גזירה gezeirah
that A will carry to C. What תוספות Tosfot says is the
exact opposite. B can go into A and B can go into
C because that's not going to create a problem. But if A
cannot go into B and C cannot go into B, why? Because
if we let A go into B, then the objects that A
moved from B will eventually find their way over to C and
that's the concern that it'll lead to the A-C case. So according
to רש"י, Rashi, you're A and C can go into B, B
can't go the opposite way, and according to תוספות, Tosfot, it's the
exact reverse because of the concern that the גמרא Gemara had said
yesterday that if we allow carrying to... if we allow this type
of carrying, it's going to lead ultimately A to C. Okay, so
two reasons why the rabbis might disagree with רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
Yes.
We're talking about carrying,
not... right?
Correct, this is all within a courtyard, it's all about carrying, carrying
objects that I should also reinforce, carrying objects that began in courtyard
A into courtyard B or began in courtyard B into courtyard A.
It's not who's doing the carrying, it doesn't matter which person is
doing the carrying, it means matters which objects are being carried.
Yeah, don't you need עקירה akirah and הנחה? hanachah?
Yes, so this is all rabbinic anyway, and it's not nobody calls
this an איסור הוצאה. issur hotza'ah. It's all in a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid. So this is like an איסור issur of like עירוב
חצירות, eiruv chatzeirot, that there's a the idea of עירוב חצירות eiruv
chatzeirot is if you don't make an עירוב חצירות eiruv chatzeirot let's
say even within A, within one courtyard,
although it's
all... one is private. So here too, you know,
the concern is that
you're right, the concern of A carrying
into C or A carrying into B if there weren't an עירוב
eruv is seen as like a violation of the עירוב חצרות. eruv
chatzeros. I don't think we're sort of calling it a type of
a type of a הוצאה, hotza'ah, a type of a rabbinic הוצאה.
hotza'ah. I don't think that's the way it's conceptualized. What you're asking
is, would we be more lenient right, would we well that's from
רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. This is all a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
but it's the need to unify distinct רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So
what you're asking is, and I'm sure there's an answer to this,
is like are there more leniencies if you do if you carry
from, you know, two courtyards that have not made an עירוב eruv
together but they're one they're רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, is there more
leniencies if you don't do an עקירה, akirah, if you don't do
a הנחה, hanachah, right? Do you conceptualize it in terms of הוצאה?
hotza'ah? I don't know, I don't think my, you know, I don't
I have not seen that at all as emphasized. It seems to
be a distinct like דרבנן de-rabbanan of, you know, of carrying in
courtyards that don't have עירוב, eruvs, you know, of moving objects from
one courtyard into another that don't that doesn't have an עירוב. eruv.
Okay, so so
again, עירוב eruv not meaning what we say when we say an
עירוב, eruv, we're talking about carrying outdoors and turning the כרמלית karmelis
into a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. This is talking that you have
רשות היחיד reshus hayachids but you're creating a unified רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid. All right, so that's the issue. The Rabbis disagree. You can
go in one direction, not in the other, either because conceptually it's
a contradiction or for תוספות Tosfos it's a גזירה. gezeirah. So now
the גמרא gemara says, כי אמריתה ki amrisah last line of מח
עמוד ב, mem ches amud beis,
that's what רב יהודה אמר, Rav Yehuda amar, first רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said this in the name, first there was an אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, then it says, כי
אמריתה קמיה דשמואל, ki amrisah kamei de-Shmuel, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says now when I said this over to שמואל, Shmuel, this position
of רב Rav that that the חכמים chachamim disagree in one direction
and not in the other,
אמר לי, amar li, he said to me, no, אף זו דברי
רבי שמעון. af zu divrei Rabbi Shimon. That's still רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon's position. I'll get back to what that line means in a
minute.
וחכמים אומרים שלשתן אסורות. ve-chachamim omrim shloshtan asuros. You're wrong. You wanted
to say that the Rabbis say you can still go one way
not the other. Debate רשי Rashi or תוספות Tosfos which way you
can go. Says no, that's within רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. The חכמים
chachamim say you can't move from any direction. A can't go to
B, B can't go to A, C can't go to B, B
can't go to C. No courtyard can go to any other. It's
not like it's okay one way and not okay the other way.
All right now what is the reason why the חכמים chachamim would
be so absolute? So again, you could say that that would be
a גזירה gezeirah reason. Even though technically you could say let's do
it תוספות Tosfos' way, that B moving to A is less of
a concern of גזירה. gezeirah. Nevertheless, the חכמים chachamim say once we
allow
any commerce between any courtyard, eventually it's going to lead to A
moving to C, and therefore we have to say it's all forbidden.
Okay, so it's not that the חכמים chachamim half agree, the חכמים
chachamim completely disagree and the חכמים chachamim say you can't go in
any direction. Now one minute, what does it mean when he says
these are the words of רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Meaning, we had
said that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you can go in all
directions, and now it's saying when you said one direction yes and
one direction no, even that is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So רשי
Rashi says what that's meaning, that means that's coming to limit רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who you thought could say
A to B and B to A, no, this idea of only
one direction, that's even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees to that. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is not as broadly permissive as you said he
was that you could go in all directions. That's the way רשי
Rashi says it. תוספות Tosfos has a slightly more elegant read because
it's strange. It sounds very clear from the משנה mishna that the
משנה mishna is totally fine whether A goes to B or B
goes to A. It sounds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is across
the board permissive. So תוספות Tosfos reads it, this idea that one
direction is still okay, that's within רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Meaning the
idea that any direction is okay is limited to רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. The חכמים chachamim say no direction is okay. All right, so
this is now, I know this is getting a little confusing, but
just to try to simplify it. You have this case A B
made an עירוב, eruv, B C made an עירוב. eruv. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says A and B can carry amongst themselves and B
and C can carry amongst themselves. That's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says. Now what do the חכמים chachamim say? So the first opinion
is the חכמים chachamim would say one direction is okay, one direction
is not okay. Debate רשי Rashi תוספות Tosfos which way, but it
doesn't matter for now, one direction is good, one is not good.
And then שמואל Shmuel says I'm sorry, any idea that any direction
is good is limited to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. The חכמים chachamim
say it's across the board not good. A can't go to B,
B can't go to A, and same with C and B. Okay,
so that's now where we're holding in the גמרא. gemara. There were
a couple of questions. We'll start with Paula. Yes?
Did she say then why bother putting these together in the first
place
if all three are no good? Yeah, well they didn't realize. Nobody
checked the הלכה halacha ahead of time.
But you're right. You're right. We're okay. Yes, the assumption still is
that you can carry in your own zone.
And now we're gonna actually see, yes, yes, okay, yeah, Charlie? But
for B might be able to carry in B and A in
A.
Yes, the assumption still is that you can carry in your own
zone, and now we're going to actually see what happens, what will
be a scenario where you might be you might even be not
able to carry in your own zone. Okay? But right now that's
the idea. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows you going, everybody agrees you
can't go A to C. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows, you know,
A within B, A to B, B to A, you know, maybe
both ways, or whatever, and according to the חכמים Chachamim don't allow
anything. That's at least שמואל's Shmuel version. Now the גמרא Gemara says:
תני כוותיה דרב יהודה אליבא דשמואל. Tani kavatei d'Rav Yehuda aliba d'Shmuel.
We taught like רב יהודה Rav Yehuda within שמואל, Shmuel, that according
to the חכמים Chachamim it's all forbidden, they don't allow any direction.
אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, said רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, this
is a ברייתא. Braitah. למה דבר דומה, L'ma davar domeh, what's this
case about the three people whose four אמות amot overlap? Remember that's
how we got into this? לשלוש
חצרות הפתוחות זו לזו פתוחות לרשות הרבים, L'shalosh chatzerot hapetuchot zo l'zo
p'tuchot l'reshut harabim, three courtyards open one to the other and open
into the street.
עירבו שתים עם האמצעית, Ervu shtayim im ha'emtzait, and A and B
combined, and B and C combined. זו מביאה מתוך ביתה ואוכלת וזו
מביאה מתוך ביתה ואוכלת, Zu mevia mitoch beitah v'ochelet v'zu mevia mitoch
beitah v'ochelet, you can bring from your house into the shared zone
and eat, let's say A can bring into the B zone and
eat, and C can bring into the B zone and eat. זו
מחזרת מותרה לתוך ביתה וזו מחזרת מותרה לתוך ביתה, Zu machazeret motarah
l'toch beitah v'zu machazeret motarah l'toch beitah, and then when you have
leftover food, you can take your leftover food from the B zone
and bring it back into A, or from the B zone and
bring it back into C if you were a C person. זו
מחזרת מותרה לתוך ביתה וזו מחזרת מותרה לתוך ביתה. Zu machazeret motarah
l'toch beitah v'zu machazeret motarah l'toch beitah. So meaning you're okay. A
and B works and B and C works for themselves. Okay, maybe
it even suggests that it works in both directions, it's a little
vague. But we'll read it תוספות's Tosafot way, that according to שמואל
Shmuel he says no, for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you can go
A-B, B-A, no problem, that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval Chachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say, שלשתן אסורות.
shloshan asurot. That was the punchline, okay? So here you see it's
very clear that it's not that the חכמים Chachamim half agree. The
חכמים Chachamim say across the board, you know, A, B, C, they
at least any shared zone is off limits. Okay, presumably each one
can do their own zone, but any shared zone is off limits.
So we have רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying it works, maybe in
one direction, maybe in both, and the חכמים Chachamim saying that at
least according to שמואל Shmuel nothing works. Okay, according to רב Rav
one direction works. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואזדא
שמואל לטעמיה. v'azda Shmuel l'taimei. שמואל Shmuel goes according to his reasoning.
דאמר שמואל, D'amar Shmuel, for שמואל Shmuel says, חצר שבין שני מבואות,
chatzer shebein shnei mavo'ot, just in case you were it was getting
too easy, we now have instead of three חצרות chatzerot we have
one חצר. chatzer. Here's your חצר, chatzer, right, and it's got all
its various houses, okay? And this חצר chatzer opens up into two
streets, okay? It opens up into two opposite streets. Now who cares
that it opens into a street? Well we'll see in a minute.
Okay, but it opens into these two streets. Now these streets, מבואות,
mavo'ot, alleyways, have opening into them other courtyards. And you might know
and remember there's an idea of שיתוף מבואות, shituf mavo'ot, that if
all courtyards want to share an alleyway, right, all these courtyards they
might have made their own עירוב, eruv, and they want to share
this alleyway, then they have to make a שיתוף מבואות. shituf mavo'ot.
All the courtyards have to then get together to use the alleyway,
okay? So this is a מבוא, mavo, like a street, okay? And
each courtyard could have made its own, but the question is using
the share. Now this opens up into two of those streets, and
it might not have made an עירוב, eruv, you know, a שיתוף,
shituf, with the other courtyards to use those streets. So let's take
a look. Okay, עירבה עם שניהם אסורה עם שניהם לא עירבה עם
שניהם אוסרת על שניהם.
erva im shneihem asura im shneihem lo
erva im shneihem oseret al shneihem.
Okay,
again that was clear. So עירבה עם שניהם, erva im shneihem, if
it did this, right, again like an A-B, B-C type of a
case,
but not together. It did this, and it did this. Okay, עירבה
עם שניהם. erva im shneihem. So it is, so what's the הלכה?
halakha? עירבה עם שניהם, erva im shneihem, the הלכה halakha is אסורה
עם שניהם. asura im shneihem. It can't use, it can't use the
street in either case. It cannot use the shared the shared zone.
Now this is like a case, right, of A, B, C. Why
can it not use the shared zone? So תוספות Tosafot says this
is just because שמואל Shmuel פוסק paskens like the חכמים Chachamim against
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, so if he פוסק paskens like the
חכמים Chachamim against רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it's his general position that
שלשתן אסורות shloshan asurot and there's no way that the shared zone
can be can be used because you know because since it would
lead to A going into, you know, eventually bringing into that zone.
That's the way תוספות Tosafot explains. רש"י Rashi tries to say, and
I'm not going to spell out how this works because it's just
going to confuse you more, that שמואל Shmuel is actually saying this
according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and but because שמואל Shmuel would
פוסק pasken הלכה כדברי המיקל בעירוב, halakha k'divrei hameikel b'eruv, and somehow
even within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon there would be a problem here,
but I will not go into that. Just for simplicity's sake תוספות
Tosfos says this is going according to the חכמים, Chachamim, so it's
an ABC. שמואל Shmuel is going like his reasoning: שלשה שאסרו, shlosha
she-asuru, no direction is okay. We've got a problem according to that.
But each one can at least carry in their own courtyard. That's
implicit. You just can't carry into this new space. Okay, so that's
the next line: לא עירבו שניהם אוסרת על שניהם. lo eirvu shneihem
oseret al shneihem. If, however, there was no עירוב, eruv, and here
it's now it's going to start to be easier, believe it or
not. If, however, there was no עירוב eruv at all, okay, then,
then we've got a problem. Then if there is no עירוב eruv
at all,
then
not only can
it not carry from one to the other, but hold on just
one second, let me just double check this before I say this.
Hold on.
Right. But even these guys here, if there was no עירוב, eruv,
then even these guys cannot carry into the street even if they
sort of made their own thing. Okay. Why not? So why is
it that even if it wasn't included, right, why is it that
their presence here makes this street forbidden to those guys? Why is
it אוסרת על שניהם? oseret al shneihem? What did it do, right,
to impinge upon that space? So we are going to see that
the idea that the point is that they basically, look, they're here,
they're caught between streets. What's the basic way the people here, you
know, go out to work? Let's assume for, let's assume that basically
if this is the main street and everybody just, you know, they
go to work this way. They all come out into this street.
So therefore, they're considered to be present in that street and therefore
you cannot make an עירוב eruv around that street and not include
all the courtyards. This is one of the courtyards. Right? Normally, right,
just a simple case, here's your מבוי, mavoi, here are all your
courtyards that open up into your מבוי. mavoi. Right? So the same
way you can't make in a courtyard half three of the houses
and not two of them, all the houses have to join together,
here too all of the courtyards have to join together. Okay. So
in this type of a case, if it's, if it's set out,
okay, not only does it mean that you can't go from like
one courtyard to the next, it even means that this street is
off limits to these guys because there is no, because now you
don't have all the courtyards joining in together. Okay, so let's take
a look about at that.
Okay, and now that's now what we're going to focus on and
this is easier to get your head around conceptually. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: היתה באחת רגילה ובאחת אינה רגילה.
hayta b'achat regila u-v'achat eina regila. It primarily went out one street
and not the others and not the other street.
זה שרגילה בו אסור וזה שאינה רגילה בו מותר. ze she-regila bo
asur v-ze she-eina regila bo mutar. So in the example I gave,
if this was the main street, the question is which street is
this courtyard part of? Which group of, you know, because a collection
of courtyards around a street. So if this was its main street,
then we basically define this as the group and therefore nobody can
use this street because you didn't include one of the courtyards. Even
if these three guys got together, they didn't include one of their
courtyards and therefore they're all, none of them can use the street.
But these guys are okay because this courtyard is considered part of
this group and not part of that group. Okay, so that's the
question and now the whole issue is which street are they primarily
part of? So the first determinant is which is the main one
that they use?
Okay, אמר רבה בר רב הונא, Amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna, so
אמר רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna says:
עירבה עם שאינה רגילה בו הותרה רגילה לעצמו. irva im she-eina regila
bo huta regila l'atzmo. He says you know what? That's by default.
By default they relate to the one that they have, that they
the street they mostly use. But they're allowed to redefine it. And
if they went ahead and they said even if they primarily use
this street, they went ahead and they said, "We're going to make
an עירוב eruv with these guys." Okay? They chose to make an
עירוב eruv with those guys, then you're allowed to do that and
to say, "I relate to, you know, I relate to, here, this
will be Broadway and this will be Central Park West." Okay? So
if they went ahead and make an עירוב eruv with these guys,
they could say we're part of the Broadway group, we're part of
the Broadway street even if it's the one they use less. And
that's then frees up these guys to make an עירוב eruv without
them and to use Central Park West without including that middle courtyard.
Okay? So yes, by default you're connected to the street you use
most, but you can if you chose to make an עירוב eruv
with the other guys, that works.
So I'll read that again: עירבה עם שאינה רגילה בו, irva im
she-eina regila bo, if she made an עירוב eruv with the guys
of the of the courtyard, the street they don't usually use, הותרה
רגילה לעצמו. huta regila l'atzmo. אם עירב עם שאינה רגילה בו, Eirev
im sheina regila bo, if he made an עירוב eruv with the
guy, with the court street, the guys of the courtyards of the
street that you don't usually use, הותרה רגילה לעצמו, Hutra regila le'atzmo,
then the one you usually use you're no longer part of and
that can work with the other courtyards. ואמר רבה בר רב הונא
אמר שמואל, Ve'amar Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar Shmuel, now רבה בר
רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna also said in the name of
שמואל. Shmuel.
אם עירבה רגילה לעצמו וזה שאינה רגילה בו לא עירב, Im irva
regila le'atzmo vezeh sheina regila bo lo eirev, so let's say the
group from Central Park West, the רגילה, regila, they made their own
לעצמו, le'atzmo, they made their own עירוב eruv without including the middle
courtyard, וזה שאינה רגילה בו לא עירב ועצמו לא עירבה, vezeh sheina
regila bo lo eirev ve'atzmo lo eirva, and neither of these two
guys
made an עירוב. eruv. So these guys do not do anything to
let them use Broadway, this guy didn't do anything, so you got
it? That's the scenario. These guys made an עירוב eruv without including
the middle courtyard and none of these guys even tried to make
an עירוב eruv around Broadway. So Broadway anyway, even if you took
away this courtyard, is off-limits to these guys because they didn't make
a שיתוף shituf of all of them to use Broadway. So remember
in that
case דוחים אותו אצל שאינה רגילה בו. dochin oto eitzel sheina regila
bo. So then we could say, even though normally we say this
goes with the Central Park West because it's רגילה, regila, unless it
very actively makes an עירוב eruv and associates itself up there with
Broadway, we normally would say that because this is the natural grouping.
Nevertheless, it doesn't hurt anyone in this case to say it's part
of the Broadway group, because if you say it's part of the
Broadway group, that means already nobody can use Broadway. So by making
them part of the Broadway group, you're not hurting anyone. You got
it? Meaning in the case where these guys made an עירוב eruv
and these guys made an עירוב eruv and these guys did not,
so whichever group you associate them with you're going to hurt because
then you're going to say that you've got a courtyard that isn't
part of your עירוב. eruv. So neither group wants these as part
of them if they haven't been part of the עירוב. eruv. And
so what would we say then? Then we would say tough luck,
you go with the street you mostly use and these guys now
have a problem. But if these guys didn't make an עירוב, eruv,
so they're not going to be hurt by saying that this is
part of the group above. So we just say, alright, we'll make
it part of the group above, we'll make life easier for people.
And then it ends by saying וכגון זה ukegon zeh and this
would be an example of כופין על מדת סדום kofin al midat
Sodom which is a very cute line. כופין על מדת סדום kofin
al midat Sodom means מדת סדום midat Sodom is an approach that
says mine is mine and yours is yours, meaning I don't want
yours but I have no responsibility to give you anything even if
it doesn't cost me
anything. Like I'm already driving to the store but I'm not going
to give you a ride, I don't want to do you any
favors, it doesn't cost me anything, I don't want to do you
any favors. So that's מדת סדום. midat Sodom. So there's a discussion
in the גמרא Gemara whether you can force somebody to allow somebody
to benefit from them even if it doesn't cost them anything. Do
you force somebody
to not stand by this מדת סדום midat Sodom but I refuse
to let you benefit from anything of mine even at no cost
to me? So the גמרא Gemara says this would be an example
of מדת סדום. midat Sodom. These guys here Broadway, if they would
say we don't want you, it doesn't hurt them. They anyway can't
use the street. So they have no entitlement to say we don't
want you to be part of us. Let them be part of
you. Nobody gets hurt here and it benefits the guys down here.
Which is pretty funny because this is like a legal principle of
which street are they a part of, but it's just saying a
way of saying conceptually, look, nobody gets hurt and this way helps
one group and doesn't hurt the other group, we might as well
define them as part of that group and not the others. You
had a question? Alright, so that's the idea of the sort of
switching the עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeirot
into the שיתוף מבואות shituf mavo'ot and which street are you a
part of will determine which one you have to make a group
with and which one you might impact to ruin their existing group.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, now we switch completely switch gears. So
getting gradually easier. First the thing about three courtyards and which direction
can you carry, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon versus the חכמים. Chachamim. Then
the issue about the courtyards between streets and which group of streets
are you part of, the one that you most often use unless
you redefine it or unless it doesn't hurt anybody to define it
in one way, that's that. Now we get to much broader statements
about the whole nature of עירוב eruv and interestingly, although the focus
of this פרק perek has completely been עירוב תחומין, eruv techumin, since
right now for the last day or so we've been talking about
עירוב חצרות, eruv chatzeirot, we get like a very central discussion about
the conceptual idea of עירוב חצרות eruv chatzeirot right here in the
middle of this פרק. perek. So let's take a look. And it's
the same אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel המקפיד על
עירובו אין עירובו עירוב. hamakpid al eiruvo ein eiruvo eiruv. If somebody
says we all join together in some loaves of bread in our
courtyard so it's all considered to be one domain. And it's a
whole shared and unified courtyard, but I say I don't want to
see anybody eating my loaf of bread. Okay. So yes, I contributed
my loaf of bread but nobody better touch it. By the when
שבת Shabbos is
over, nobody can, it better be just the way I just the
way I gave. So אינו עירובו עירוב, eino eruvo eruv, you're not
really part of the עירוב. eiruv. And therefore, everybody's got a problem
because now you don't have an עירוב eiruv and nobody can carry
in the courtyard. Okay, because the whole idea of the עירוב eiruv
is to make it a unified which means and here you're keeping
your sort of presence symbolized by the bread as set apart from
everybody else. So מה, ma,
so and that's what he says: המקפיד אינו עירובו עירוב. hamakpid eino
eruvo eruv. מה שמו? Ma shemo? What's it called? עירוב שמו. Eiruv
shemo. The whole point is that it should be an עירוב eiruv
because that you love. First of all it's very fascinating that sort
of inferring הלכה halacha from like the name of something. And number
two, it's like it's missing obviously more of the explanation. What do
you mean by the word עירוב? eiruv? So רש"י Rashi actually says
two things. The most obvious thing is עירוב eiruv means like מעורב,
me'urav, which means mixed together and unified as opposed to standing apart.
But רש"י Rashi also throws in a line רש"י Rashi says, if
you look four lines down in the wide line, עירוב שמו, eiruv
shemo, רש"י Rashi says שכולם מעורבין, she'kulam me'uravin, mixed together in one
unit. And then he says ומרוצין בו, u'merutzin bo, they should be
sort of
finding favor in one another's eyes, a sense of
camaraderie. שלא ימחה זה בחברו אלא שותפות נוחה ועריבה. Shelo yimcheh zeh
be'chaveiro ella shutfus nocha ve'areiva. He specifically says עריבה, areiva, because עריבה,
areiva,
עירוב eiruv does not just mean mixed together, it means pleasant. Okay,
so עריב areiv means pleasant. So therefore there should be a pleasantness,
there should be a sense of community created by this and you're
actually setting yourself apart from the community. Okay, so very nice idea.
If somebody wanted to be a real,
whatever S.O.B., he could just say yeah
he could just say I'm not joining in the עירוב eiruv and
then nobody's right.
Yeah well we'll get to that about people that stand that sit
out of the עירוב eiruv and how you deal with those cases.
But here he's trying to participate but he's still setting himself apart.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says: רבי חנינא אמר עירובו עירוב.
Rabbi Chanina amar eruvo eruv. No actually it does work even if
you say I don't want anyone touching my bread. אלא שנקרא מאנשי
ורדינא, Ella she'nikra me'anshei vardina, but you are called from one of
the people of Vardina which was apparently a place known for its
miserliness. So that's interesting in the immediate context of the גמרא Gemara
before about כופין על אנשי סדום. kofin al anshei sdom. So people
say okay you're stingy, you're miserly, but at the end of the
day even begrudgingly you participated it's enough to say even when we
have a community it could be a real-world community it doesn't have
to be an ideal community. So even in a real community yeah
you have your stuff but you're still part of the community. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: החולק את עירובו אינו עירוב.
acholek es eruvo eino eiruv. Now not only that let's say you
don't say I don't want anybody eating my עירוב. eiruv. You just
say I want to keep my loaf of bread in a separate
basket. We're all keeping them there at Charlie's house, but I want
to keep my loaves in a separate basket. So it's also not
good. כמאן? Keman? גמרא Gemara says כמאן כבית שמאי? keman keBeis Shammai?
Are you saying like בית שמאי Beis Shammai דתניא, detanya, we quoted
this before, חמישה שגבו את עירובן, chamisha shegav'u es eiruvam, five people
joined together in an עירוב eiruv ונתנו בשני כלים venasnu beshnei keilim
and they divided it into two vessels. בית שמאי אומרים אינו עירוב,
Beis Shammai omrim eino eiruv, it's not an עירוב eiruv because it's
not all unified. ובית הלל אומרים הרי עירוב, uBeis Hillel omrim harei
eiruv, it is good. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא
בית הלל, afilu teima Beis Hillel, this he'd say this even according
to בית הלל. Beis Hillel. עד כאן לא קאמרי בית הלל התם,
Ad kan lo ka'amri Beis Hillel hasam, why does בית הלל Beis
Hillel say it's good there when you divide it into two כלים?
keilim? אלא דמליא למנא ואייתר, Ella d'malyan lemana ve'aytar, you tried to
put it all in one vessel but it wouldn't fit so you
had leftover. So perforce you divided it. So בית הלל Beis Hillel
says fine. אבל היכא דפלגי מפלג, Aval heicha d'palgei miflag, when you
are intentionally ensuring that your loaves are kept apart, that's very different.
That's not like you couldn't put it together it's like one person
בדווקא bedavka wanted his stuff separate, לא, lo, that would not be
good that is not enough of a unified sense of an עירוב.
eiruv. ותרתי למה לי? Ve'tarti lamma li? Now why did שמואל Shmuel
have to say both cases, a physically separate or a not wanting
people to touch it and physically separate? צריכי, Tzrichi, you need both
cases. אי אשמעינן התם, I shemi'inan hasam, if you just told me
the first case about saying don't eat my עירוב, eiruv, משום דקפיד,
mishum d'kapid, that's because you care and you're particular that nobody touch
it. So you really say hands off, that makes it separate. אבל
הכא אימא לא, Aval hacha ima lo, but here even if you
want it kept in a separate vessel but maybe you're okay if
other people eat it, so kept physically separate is not as big
of a deal. Or you could have said the opposite. אי אשמעינן
הכא, I shemi'inan hacha, if you'd said it here משום דפלגי מפלג,
mishum d'palgei miflag, because it's physically separate. אבל התם, Aval hasam, there
where it's physically all together it's just you said you don't want
anybody to eat it, אימא לא, ima lo, maybe that wouldn't have
been a problem, צריכי, tzrichi, you need both cases. But clearly רב
יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel very much demands a great
sense of unification symbolized by the עירוב eiruv and something that challenges
that might actually... destroy its function as an עירוב. eruv. אמר ליה
רב אבא לרב יהודה בבי מצראתא, Amar lei Rav Abba le-Rav Yehuda
be-bei matzarta,
so רב אבא Rav Abba said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, who
was the one quoting שמואל, Shmuel, and he said this to them
in the like sort of oil-press, olive-press, just that's parenthetical, דבי רב,
debei Rav, the רב's Rav olive-press, דבי רב זכאי, debei Rav Zakai,
excuse me, רב זכאי's Rav Zakai olive-press. מי אמר שמואל החולק את
עירובו אינו עירוב? Mi amar Shmuel hacholek es eruvo einu eruv? Did
שמואל Shmuel really say this, that if you set it apart, it's
not good, it's not good? ואמר שמואל, Va'amar Shmuel, but שמואל Shmuel
says, בית שמניחין בו עירוב אין צריך ליתן את הפת, Bayis shemenichin
bo eruv ein tzarich litten es hapas, that the house that you
put the עירוב eruv in does not have to contribute to the
bread. So we all chip together, everybody threw in a loaf of
bread, we all brought it over to Charlie's house, we put it
in Charlie's house, Charlie doesn't have to give a loaf of bread.
Now, why is that? So the גמרא Gemara thinks that the reason
is the following. Where are we? מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the
reason? לאו משום דאמרינן דכיון דמנח בסל כמאן דמנח הכא דמי? Lav
mishum de'amrinan dekeivan demanach besal kman demanach hacha dami?
Isn't it because we say that even though because Charlie has bread
for שבת, Shabbos, you know, it's somewhere else, it's in his bread
basket, so the bread in Charlie's bread basket counts together with the
bread in the עירוב. eruv. That's why we think Charlie doesn't have
to give bread, because somewhere else in his house he has bread
and that's as if it's all together. So you see the עירוב
eruv doesn't have to be physically together. Okay. הכא נמי, Hacha nami,
why don't we say when the guy wants to keep it separate,
כיון דמנח בסל כמאן דמנח הכא דמי, keivan demanach besal kman demanach
hacha dami, even if it's not here, it's like it's all together
and that should be okay? Now an obvious distinction could be that
in one case you want to keep it separate, in the other
case it's just like accidentally it's not together, but the גמרא Gemara
has an even stronger answer. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda said back, התם אף על פי שאין פת, Hasam af
al pi she'ein pas, you know what? It works in Charlie, Charlie
doesn't have to give the bread, not because he has bread somewhere
else in his house. Even if he had no bread anywhere else
in his house, he was eating out for שבת Shabbos lunch, he
had absolutely no bread in his house, even so he doesn't have
to participate in the עירוב. eruv. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the
reason? דכולהו הכא דיירי, Dekulhu hacha dary, they all live here. We
all are coming and living in Charlie's house this שבת. Shabbos. Because
here's an interesting question: when we say the idea of עירוב eruv
is to unify us all, are we unified all as now like
it's all big one territory, you know, it's all communally owned space
and we're all together as a coherent community? That's probably what you
would most naturally think. But now the גמרא Gemara is saying that
according to שמואל's Shmuel idea that Charlie doesn't have to participate, that's
not what it is. When we all get together in the bread
and we put it in Charlie's house, it's not all we're just
one big community, it's actually we're all living in Charlie's house for
שבת. Shabbos. That's what it symbolizes. So actually the entire courtyard and
all of our houses for this שבת Shabbos are essentially Charlie's. Okay,
so that's a bit of a different idea. The other idea I
have to tell you is a lot nicer, that it's all one
as a community, but here it says no, no, no, it's all
one person. The idea of an עירוב eruv is you all join
together and put it in one person's house, that makes it all
as if it all belongs to that one person.
Like in עירוב תחומין, eruv techumin, right, where you say this is
the place?
Right, exactly, and we'll see that in a minute, that the place
of the bread is like where we're all living, exactly. And it's
not just so because of that he says exactly that, and we're
actually going to see something very similar to that in a second,
that's why Charlie doesn't have to participate, which is an interesting idea
because you would have thought, given שמואל's Shmuel statements before that so
מחמיר machmir about, you know, not setting apart and everything coming together,
you would have more maybe wanted to promote an idea of a
complete collective rather than it's all sort of becoming one with
Charlie.
Yes, Charlie. So if where the food is is where you're really
living in terms of שבת, Shabbos, maybe we should light candles where
we're eating.
That part they did not demand. Okay, anyways, so let's take a
look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
So it's as if Charlie's providing like rent-free space?
Right, so
you know, that's his contribution, not bread.
Oh, okay, that's a nice way of saying it, but again, it
seems to be going further than that. It seems to be saying
in principle Charlie doesn't have to participate because the whole idea is
to make us all connected to him. He doesn't have to be
part of the group. But again, you know, yeah, go ahead.
Do you have to do this every week or once?
No, you can do it once and stipulate that, you know, it
would work for the whole year, right, as long as the stuff
doesn't go moldy, which is why we use מצות. matzos. Okay, yes,
alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, now
here again, a statement in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, עירוב משום
קנין. Eruv mishum kinyan. עירוב Eruv is not like we were just
saying a minute ago that it's like we all start שבת Shabbos
where our bread is. No, the idea is we give bread and
therefore, the way רש"י Rashi explains with this idea that it's all
based on the house we're staying in, the עירוב eruv is in,
everybody gives bread to Charlie, and Charlie in exchange gives people rights,
this is maybe more legalistic, rights to his house. Okay, so therefore,
it's like an exchange. You give the bread and in exchange you
get a, you know, a right to use Charlie's house and we
all become unified that way. עירוב, Eruv, which is a very strange
idea. to think of it as transactional that way, and it's also
strange because it doesn't seem consistent with שמואל's Shmuel emphasis before that
it's about bringing people together. Here it's more about just transacting and
taking part ownership in Charlie's house. ואם תאמר מפני מה אין קונין
במעה, V'im tomar mipnei mah ein konin b'ma'ah, so if that's what
it's about, why do we have to use bread? Why can't we
just all give Charlie like a dollar? מפני שאינו מצוי בערבי שבתות,
Mipnei she'eino matzui b'arvei shabbatos, because ערב שבת erev Shabbos you're not
handling your money. So therefore since maybe this all gets done at
the last minute, they said do it with bread. But essentially we're
all buying a share in Charlie's house. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so היכא דעירב במעה? heicha d'eirev b'ma'ah? Okay, but if you actually
went ahead and בדיעבד b'diavad did an עירוב eruv by all putting,
you know, giving Charlie money rather than by putting bread in his
house, why shouldn't it work if it's all about a transaction? גזירה
שמא יאמרו מה עיקר, Gezeirah shema yomru mah ikar,
so because that'll lead people to thinking that it really is about
money, וזימנין דלא שכיח מה, v'zimnin d'la shechiach mah, and there'll be
times they don't have the money and they'll forget about the idea
of bread and they'll overemphasize the money ולא אתי לאיערובי בפת, v'lo
asi l'eiruvi b'pas, and they won't use the bread ואתי לאיקלקולי, v'asi
l'itkalkuli, and then you'll sort of ruin the עירוב eruv in the
sense that you won't be able to have an עירוב. eruv. So
it seems a little bit extreme all of this, like you know,
I mean just because we allow it once as an exception, we're
afraid the exception will overrule, will dominate. But if you say the
idea is that it's all about a transaction, so within that mindset
you could understand why you're afraid that using money will come to
be will come to dominate. Okay, so that's a very strange idea
and it's particularly strange given like I said everything שמואל Shmuel said
before which much more speaks about like a symbolic unification as opposed
to some type of a transaction of giving Charlie money and therefore
owning a piece of his property. So that's one version. Now we're
going to see one that's I think is much more intuitive and
was what Dov was saying before. רבה אמר, Rabbah amar,
רבה Rabbah says עירוב משום דירה. eruv mishum dirah. No, like Dov
said it's just like עירוב תחומין eruv techumin where the bread is
is where you start שבת. Shabbos. So because we had bread in
Charlie's house, we all started together in Charlie's house. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What would be a practical difference between these
two approaches? איכא בינייהו כלי ופחות משוה פרוטה וקטן. Icha beinaihu kli
u'pachos mi'shaveh perutah v'katan. Three things that would make a difference. Number
one, כלי, kli, a vessel. If it really is because of a
transaction, so we said you don't use money because nobody has money
in their house right before שבת, Shabbos, nobody has money around. But
let's say not money and not bread, why can't I just leave,
I don't know, you know my shirt at Charlie's house? Because it'll
be also like a transaction. I give him my shirt, he gives
me rights to his property. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is saying
according to שמואל Shmuel in principle you could do that. In principle
you don't have to give bread. In principle you can give a
vessel, maybe not money but a vessel, it's all about a transaction.
Again very very strange. What is the case about פחות משוה פרוטה?
pachos mi'shaveh perutah? Let's say the bread isn't worth a פרוטה. perutah.
So if it's again about transactional, so you can't use something less
than a פרוטה, perutah, it doesn't work for sense of a transaction.
If it's the idea that's bread is where it has enough for
a meal, it's where I start שבת, Shabbos, who cares how much
it's worth? Okay, so it's like what is it they say? The
cynic knows
the price of everything and the value of
nothing. Anyway fine, so if it's about bread, if it's about bread
as symbolizing presence and eating or whatever, it doesn't matter how much
it costs. Okay, and how about קטן? katan? So קטן katan cannot
engage in a financial transaction. So therefore if it's about a financial
transaction, קטן katan doesn't work. So what which side of the equation
does קטן katan doesn't work? רש״י Rashi says the קטן katan can't
even deposit the עירוב eruv for me, like if I can't send
my kid to contribute it because he can't be part of either
side of the transaction. תוספות Tosafos says no, he wouldn't be able
to be the homeowner, he couldn't transfer ownership of the house to
the group, but maybe he could contribute to the עירוב. eruv. In
the end, this is the idea of this as a transactional model
is very strange and it does not seem at all consistent with
שמואל's Shmuel statements before which are very much about the symbolic unification.
Okay, so how do we rule? If you look at the end
of the תוספות Tosafos וקטן, v'katan, like five lines before the word
תוספות Tosafos ואמר, v'amar, he says ונראה דהלכה כרבה דאמר עירוב משום
דירה. v'nirah d'halachah k'Rabbah d'amar eruv mishum dirah. כפרק קמא דרבי יוחנן,
k'perek kama d'Rabbi Yochanan, שוכר כמעריב דמי, socher k'maariv dami, ומפרש מאי
מעריב בפחות משוה פרוטה. u'mifaresh mai maariv b'pachos mi'shaveh perutah. He quotes
a lot of other גמרות Gemaros that speak like you can use
less than a פרוטה perutah and all this other evidence that yes,
we rule that it's משום דירה. mishum dirah. So by the way,
this just shows you the value of sticking through with things because
we just got through this really like complicated גמרא Gemara and then
we got this big prize here at the end, a nice straight
discussion about, you know, what is the symbolism of עירוב eruv about?
Is it about bringing everybody to unify, that nice רש״י Rashi about
עריבה, areiva, pleasantness, a sense of a whole community? If you try
to stand out, you know, in somewhat separate your עירוב, eruv, that
could be symbolically problematic according to שמואל. Shmuel. And then in the
end this idea which would seem consistent with שמואל, Shmuel, רבה's Rabbah
position that the idea is where the bread is, that's where we're
all living. And that sort of is defined as that we're all
sort of living together, and I should say again, this idea that,
if it weren't for that position that Charlie didn't have to contribute,
the owner of the house didn't have to contribute, I think you
would have said that we're all just one corporate community and we're
all equal. By saying the idea that Charlie doesn't have to contribute
is taking away a little bit from this; it's not saying we're
all equal, it's saying we're all living together with Charlie. Charlie's invited
us all to his house, so we're all brought together, but again,
not as some, you know, equal corporate entity, but we're all brought
together as living in Charlie's house. And then you did have this
very strange position which seems to be against everything of this, that
sees it much more as transactional, as getting a piece of Charlie's
house, but that seems to really be, you know, a more marginal
position. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara wraps up with this.
אמר ליה אביי לרבה, Amar leh Abaye le-Rabbah, Abaye said to Rabbah,
לדידך קשיא לשמואל קשיא, le-didach kashya le-Shmuel kashya, I've got a problem
according to both your approaches, whether it's transactional or whether it's like
you're living there. הא תניא, Ha tanya, we've got a ברייתא, baraita,
חמישה שגבו את עירובן, chamishah she-gavei et eruvam, five people made their
עירוב, eruv, one courtyard made their עירוב, eruv, כשמוליכין את עירובן למקום
אחר, keshe-molichin et eruvam le-makom acher, now courtyard A wants to join
in together with courtyard B. Don't worry, it's not hard like the
other case. אחד מוליך לכולן, Echad molich le-kulan, so you can send
one guy from courtyard A to contribute to courtyard B, okay, you
don't need them all to do it together. So גמרא Gemara says,
why is that? הוא ניהו דקקני, Hu ney de-ka-kani, וסו
לא, ve-su lo, if it's an idea of acquisition, so the one
guy Reuven from courtyard A, he gets an acquisition into courtyard B,
but not the rest of the courtyard. Or let's say it's an
idea of living, הוא ניהו דקדייר, hu ney de-ka-dayer, so now Reuven
is also living in courtyard B, but not everybody else from A,
וסו לא, ve-su lo, and not everybody else. So the question is,
okay, but like whatever model you have, why does one person work
for the whole courtyard? And the answer is obvious. אמר ליה, Amar
leh, לא לדידי קשיא ולא לשמואל קשיא, lo le-didi kashya ve-lo le-Shmuel
kashya, it's not hard for me or to Shmuel. שליחות דכולהו קעביד,
Shlichut de-kulu ka-avid, when Reuven goes from A to B to participate
in their courtyard, he represents all of courtyard A, right, which is
what you would have said anyway regardless of what model you would
have used. So yes, whether it's about acquisition or presence, when one
courtyard joins with another, they send one guy and he becomes their
representative. Okay, אמר רבה אמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב, Amar
Rabbah amar Rav Chama bar Guria amar Rav, הלכה כרבי שמעון. halachah
ke-Rabbi Shimon. By the way, if you were wondering about A, B,
and C and all the stuff we discussed before, we rule like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that it does work, that A can carry
into B and B can carry into C, you just can't go
from A to C, okay, that whole previous discussion. Okay, but that
was a very nice גמרא Gemara about the nature and symbolism of
עירוב. eruv. Now for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that is coming up to...
all right, all right, הילולא דרשב״י, hillula de-Rashbi, yes.
We talked about that one guy being the שליח shaliach for the
whole for the other five. At one point in your ABC model,
didn't we talk about A and B making their עירוב eruv first?
Yes. And
no longer being A
and B, but being AB? Yes.
And then being able to contract with C?
Yeah, that's what the גמרא Gemara asked. But the גמרא Gemara says
because we rejected... because the גמרא Gemara said since A set out
that second transaction and didn't have any representative going to C, it
makes it clear
that they weren't about A
anymore, it was now AB. Yeah, but you know, not totally. I
mean, you have the substrata.
I understand, I understand.
Those other five can go ahead and represent...
Right, that was the גמרא's Gemara question, but the answer was that
you still have a substrata of AB even with an overlay, so
and they were able to break out, but that was exactly the
גמרא's Gemara question before. Okay, let's now move to the next משנה
mishnah where we get back to עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. מי שבא
בדרך, Mi she-ba ba-derech, you're on a journey. וחשכה לו, ve-chashkah lo,
and it's getting dark. Now, and you're just right outside your home,
you know, almost there, only four thousand אמות amot away from your
home. It's about to be
שבת. Shabbat. והיה מכיר אילן או גדר, ve-hayah makkir ilan o geder,
and you know of a tree or of a wall that's midpoint
between you and your home, and if you were to have be
able to start שבת Shabbat where that tree or wall was, you'd
be
perfect. You'd be at the outer edge of your right...
Here's you,
here's a tree, right, and here's your home, okay, and there's basically
two thousand אמות amot each way. So if you could only start
שבת Shabbat here, then that would be your תחום, techum, you'd be
able to walk to the tree and walk from the tree to
your home. Okay, so you'd like to be able to make an
עירוב eruv there, but you're two thousand אמות amot away. What are
you going to do? And it's about to be שבת. Shabbat. So...
ואמר, ve-amar, and you said, שביתתי תחתיו, shevitati tachtav, you made a
declaration without putting any bread there, you said, my שבת Shabbat should
be under the tree. לא אמר כלום, Lo amar klum, גורנישט העלפן.
gornisht helfen. Why? Not because you just spoke without actually doing anything,
because you didn't say specifically, you weren't more precise where your עירוב
eruv began. If you said שביתתי בעיקרו, shevitati be-ikaro,
underneath the tree, well, you know, the tree has a big canopy,
so that's... you don't know exactly where, but if you said at
the root of the tree, meaning... at the trunk of the tree
and you were very specific, then it's good. נמצא מהלך משחשיכה ארבעת
אלפים אמה. Nimtza m'haleich m'chasheicha arba'as alafim amah. Then you can get—I
skipped a line. Yeah, it is. I'm sorry. שביתתי בעיקרו מהלך ממקום
רגליו עד עיקרו אלפיים אמה, Shvisosi b'ikaro m'haleich m'makom raglav ad ikaro
alpayim amah, you can get 2,000 אמות amos if you're within 2,000
אמות amos you can get to the trunk of the tree. ומיקרו
U'mikaro and literally the root, but בביתו אלפיים אמה, b'beiso alpayim amah,
and then you can get from the tree to your house 2,000
אמות. amos. נמצא מהלך משחשיכה ארבעת אלפים אמה. Nimtza m'haleich m'chasheicha arba'as
alafim amah. So even after it got dark, you could walk in
a straight line 4,000 אמות amos because you've designated your thing there.
Now of course, what's interesting and we've seen this discussion before is,
I thought for an עירוב eiruv to work, you had to have
either the bread there, or you had to physically be present. Okay,
so here you're not doing anything, you're just verbally designating. So whoever
has to make an עירוב eiruv will just stay home and I'll
say it's, you know, it's over there. So it might be a
particular leniency that they allowed for the guy caught in the middle
of the street. He's not sitting at home. He's going out to
place his עירוב eiruv and he just hasn't gotten there yet. Okay,
and there we might have a certain leniency, but it is quite
interesting that you can do it just totally verbally. Let's see the
rest of the
משנה. Mishnah. Okay. Now, אם אינו מכיר, Im eino makir, let's say
you don't know a specific place. You don't know of any tree
that's within 2,000 אמות. amos. או שאינו בקי בהלכה, O sheino baki
b'halachah, or you're not smart enough to know that you could do
something like this. You don't know the law. ואמר שביתתי במקומי. V'amar
shvisosi bimkomi.
So you didn't have a tree to designate. So you just said,
fine, I'll start שבת Shabbos where I'm standing right now. You're not
going to get home, but you wanted to not limit yourself to
four אמות. amos. זכה לו מקומו אלפיים אמה לכל רוח. Zachah lo
mekomo alpayim amah l'chol ruach. Fine,
then you go from where you start 2,000 אמה amah in every
direction. תוספות Tosafot points out that you don't really have to say
anything. It just says you said because the first part of the
משנה Mishnah says you said. But you know, the discussions before were
if you're asleep, but you know, then you maybe only have four
אמות, amos, you don't have a place. But תוספות Tosafot says if
you're awake and you're there at שבת Shabbos and you haven't said
anything, obviously where you're standing is where you begin שבת Shabbos even
without saying anything and you have 2,000 אמות. amos. Okay, now we
have an interesting discussion, the same way we had a whole discussion
how to measure the four אמות, amos, we have an interesting discussion
how to measure the 2,000 אמות. amos. So what are these 2,000
אמות? amos? עגולות, Agulot, they are a circle. דברי רבי חנינא בן
אנטיגנוס. Divrei Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos. וחכמים אומרים, V'chachamim omrim, מרובעות. meruba'ot.
The חכמים chachamim say you can draw a square. כטבלא מרובעת, K'tavla
meruba'at, like a square tableau, כדי שיהא נשכר לזויות, k'dei she'yehei niskar
l'zaviyos, so you get the corners. Obviously, there's a big difference, right?
If you're here,
how do you draw your 2,000 אמות? amos? Do you draw a
circle, right? in which you're the—and you're the radius—and you're the center
and it's 2,000 אמות? amos? Or do you draw a square and
you're the center? And then you get the additional, right, corners and
get more space. Right. And then the question is also which direction
do you draw the square in? Right? If it's a circle, it
doesn't matter. But if it's a square, do you draw the square
like that? You know, do you draw the square like that? Right?
It's going to matter what space it is in terms of which
direction you draw the square. Okay, but that's what they say. We
will see more about that. Okay, now וזו היא שאמרו העני מערב
ברגליו. V'zo hi she'amru he'ani m'areiv b'raglav. This case about getting stuck
out in the street, we quoted this משנה Mishnah before, is when
they said a poor person can—doesn't need bread—can do it with his
presence. And here you're poor effectively because you don't have access to
any bread to do it. You're stuck in the middle of the
road. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, אין לנו אלא עני. ein
lanu ela ani. This idea you don't need bread, you can do
it in person, is only if you have no other choice. You're
poor or you're effectively poor. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, אחד
עני ואחד עשיר. echad ani v'echad ashir. You know what, it doesn't
matter, even if you had bread accessible, you're allowed to do it
in person. לא אמרו מערבין בפת, Lo amru m'arvin b'pas, they only
said you use the bread, אלא להקל על העשיר, ela l'hakel al
he'ashir, שלא יצא ויערב ברגליו. shelo yeitzei v'yeareiv b'raglav. They just did
it to make it easier, you know, that you don't have to
go out and wait for it to become dark and stand there.
You want to put bread there and come home, or you want
to send somebody to put bread there, גזונטהייט. Gezuntheit. But there's no
problem if you really want to physically be there. That's what the
bread symbolizes, so you might as well actually physically be there. Okay,
so we saw this before, debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, whether they only allowed in a necessary circumstance,
you know, you to do it in person, or you can always
do it in person. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
about what happens when you try to start under the tree without
a specific place. So מאי לא אמר כלום? Mai lo amar klum?
What does it mean if you said "under the tree" without designating
the space? It's worthless, it doesn't mean anything. אמר רב, Amar Rav,
לא אמר כלום כל עיקר. lo amar klum kol ikar. It is
completely worthless, דאפילו לתחתיו של אילן לא מצי אזיל. d'afilu l'tachtav shel
ilan lo matzi azil. You can't even get under the tree. What
does that mean? It means
that,
right, right. So רש"י Rashi basically says, you said you want to
go under the tree, but you didn't say where under the tree.
So since you didn't say where under the tree—right, the "under the
tree" is like, you know, there's a space—you didn't say where, so
you didn't effectively put your עירוב eiruv here or designate your שבת
Shabbos starting here because you weren't specific. But you also made it
clear you didn't want to start שבת Shabbos where you were. So
this isn't your space and this isn't your space. this isn't your
space, so you only have four אמות, amos, you're totally stuck, okay?
You've totally ruined it for yourself. That's what רב Rav says. שמואל
Shmuel has a much more sympathetic approach. So that's why רב Rav
says you can't even get to the tree, you can't get anywhere,
you're totally stuck. ושמואל אמר לא אמר כלום לביתו. V'Shmuel amar lo
amar klum l'beiso. No,
given that you weren't specific, you can't make it all the way
to your house. אבל לתחתיו של אילן מצי אזיל. Aval l'tachtav shel
ilan matzi azil. You can get to the tree. שנעשה תחתיו של
אילן חמר גמל. shenasei tachtav shel ilan chamor gamal. And the space...
I'll read the whole thing and then I'll explain it. The underside
of the tree became like that camel-donkey driver, you know, you're pulled
in both directions, opposite directions. בא למוד מן הצפון מודדין לו מן
הדרום. Ba limdod min hatzafon modedin lo min hadarom. If you want
to go north, we'll start you in the south. בא למוד מן
הדרום מודדין לו מן הצפון. Ba limdod min hadarom modedin lo min
hatzafon. If you want to go south, we'll start you north. Which
means what? Here's what he says. He says, right, let's say this
space under the tree is let's say 20 אמות. amos. Let's say
it is 10 אמות amos in each direction, okay? The space, and
you don't know where in these 10 אמות amos you start your
עירוב eruv because you said under the tree, you weren't specific where.
So what he says is we just consider it as a ספק.
safek. Maybe your עירוב eruv starts here, maybe your עירוב eruv starts
here. So, what's the idea? You'll have 20 אמות amos that's in
doubt. Right? If you want to go 2,000 אמות amos in this
direction, we say, 'Whoa, no, no, no, maybe this is your עירוב.'
eruv. So you don't have 2,000 אמות amos from this point, you
only have 2,000 אמות amos from this point. So if you want
to go לדרום, l'darom, מודדין לו מן הצפון. modedin lo min hatzafon.
So you can only go 1,980 this way. Now, if you wanted
to get from this point to your home and it was exactly
2,000 אמות amos to your home, you've got a problem. You can't
walk in your door because maybe your עירוב eruv started here and
you only have 1,980 from that point. So that's what it means:
you can't get all the way to your home assuming it's exactly
2,000 אמות amos because this space underneath the tree is up for
grabs and we're always going to give you... you're being pulled in
both directions. We're always going to measure it, you know, in the
way that is, you know, is being מחמיר. machmir. Because maybe you
started on the other side. So you always are going to lose
effectively 20 אמות amos to your עירוב eruv in whichever direction you're
trying to go. So that is the debate. שמואל Shmuel has a
very small implication of not knowing the place. According to רב Rav
it's quite extreme. It basically is that since you didn't specify the
space, you don't have any space and you're totally stuck. And the...
let's just read... we have two more minutes, so let's just read
the first sentence on דף נ daf nun which spells out the
reasoning of
רב. Rav. אמר רבה מאי טעמא דרב? Amar Rabbah mai ta'ama d'Rav?
What's the reasoning of רב? Rav? משום דלא מסיים אתריה. Mishum d'lo
mesayem atrei. Because you didn't designate the space and not designating the
space doesn't give you... make it a ספק safek and it's either,
you know, this edge of the tree or that edge of the
tree. Not specifying gives
you nothing. So you made it clear you don't want to start
שבת Shabbos where you were, you didn't start שבת Shabbos effectively in
any place, and therefore you are totally stuck. So more about this
tomorrow. Alright.
I guess the first thing you have to do when you buy
a new house is plant trees 2,000 אמות.
amos. Something like that.